# 大家好 今天摘點這個梅子回去
Hi everyone! Today we're gonna pick some plums.
# 這個梅子還沒熟哦 我們先把它摘下來
The plums are still green. But we're gonna pick them first.
# 用來
Then we can,
# 用來那個 用來泡酒
we can, you know, we can make some umeshu (plum liquor).
# 現在這個梅子好酸 好澀
Now the plums are still very sour, and don't taste good at all.
# 但是這個用來做那個青梅酒是特別好的
But they are excellent for making plum liquor.
# 聞聞都有它的那個香味
The fragrance is very significant.
# 它的香味已經出來啦
The fragrance is already there.
# 你看 這樹上 這樹上就有哦
Look! In this tree, you can see them in this tree.
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one.
# 誒 是不是
Oy! Isn't it?
# 我在那裡看到了但是我太矮(摘不到)
I see a lot over there. But I'm too short.
You mean you can't pick?
# 我把你一扔扔到那裡去 掛到樹上 然後你就可以摘啦
Shall I throw you over there, so that you can pick whatever you want while you're hanging on the tree?
# 好不好
Shall I?
# 行不行
Isn't it a good idea?
Yes or no?
# 我
I ah...
# 行
yes...
# 行是不行
You said yes, didn't you?
# 好 我要上樹了 摘不到了這裡
Alright! I need to climb onto the tree. I can't pick any here.
# 太高啦
It's too high.
# 這裡可以摘
I can pick some here.
# 你怎麼上去
How are you going to climb?
# 這裡可以把它拉下來 我拉下來你來摘好不好
I can pull it down here. I pull it down and then you pick the plums, alright?
# 嗯
Alright!
# 看到沒有 摘不摘的[SIC]到
Can you see them? Can you pick them?
# 這裡都好個
Here are a lot!
# 我要上去
I need to go up.
# 快點 你幫我接
C'mon! Catch it for me.
# 你把那個袋口張開來 我來丟 (註︰那是魚網，但他說袋就袋吧)
Keep the bag open. I'm gonna throw it in.
# 看下還有沒有
Let me see if there are still any.
# 哪裡還有
Are there still any somewhere?
# 沒有了 沒有了換另外一棵樹枝 這裡
No more? No more, then let's move to another branch. Here.
# 走開走開
Go 'way, go 'way.
# 來
C'mon!
# 誒呦 長得矮
Ayo! I'm too short.
# 這些都沒摘到就飛走啦 (註︰沒看懂，唯有照字面譯)
These have already flown away before I can pick them.
# 還有
More!
# 誒呦
Ayo!
# 胡韋汝你敢不敢上樹
Hu Weiru, dare you climb the tree?
# 我不敢
No, I dare not.
# 你 你還敢啊
You, you still dare?
# 我肯定敢
Sure! Why not?
# 我有甚麼不敢的
Nothing can scare me.
# 爸爸 你敢不敢上
Daddy, do you dare to climb?
# 敢啊
Yup!
# 男生就敢上樹
The boys dare to climb.
# 我是女生 我 太小了 不會上樹
I'm a girl. I'm...too small. I can't climb.
# 我好怕我掉下來
I may fall. I'm scared.
# 你看這裡 好多啊 一樹都是
Look! Here are a lot, all over the tree.
# 今天我要泡一大缸
I'm gonna make a huge jar,
# 一 一大缸酒來
a, a huge jar of plum liquor.
# 剛好 這個帽派上用場啦 我口袋裡面都放滿啦
Good! This hat is finally useful now. My pockets are already full.
# 你看 這裡 好多
Look! Here are, a lot!
# 你看 全都是
Look! All are,
# 很大的哦
really big, you know.
# 好靚
Beautiful!
# 帽子太小
The hat is too small.
# 帶個大帽子來
You should have come with a bigger hat.
# 你看 現在這帽子都裝滿啦
Look! Now the hat is also full.
# 你的頭也不長大一點
Why don't you have a larger head?
# 摘的帽子那麼小
You hat is so tiny.
# 還有好多哦 你看上面
There are still a lot. Look, up there!
# 還有好多
There are still a lot.
# 我把那個拉過來摘
I'm gonna pull it to me.
# 又要保証自己的安全
But I still need to ensure my own safety.
# 所以要插在這裡 要不然就會 容易掉下去
So I need to stay between the branches, to prevent myself, from falling.
# 這樣插就不會掉下去啦
I won't fall when I'm between the branches.
# 好多 (註︰沒有原字幕)
A lot!
# 你看這個帽子
Have a look at the hat!
# 這個帽子都
The hat is already,
# 滿啦 全滿
already full, completely full.
# 要怪就怪這個帽子太小
It's too bad that the hat is far too small.
# 誒呀 又掉了一顆
Eya! I've dropped another one.
# 這個帽子
The hat...
# 先下去 先下去
Get down first, get down first.
# 下去先後我再上來
Get down first and then I'll come back.
# 我把這個空掉
Let me empty the hat first.
# 空掉之後我再上來
I'll come back after emptying it.
# 我們兩個也給我上來
Get down, you two guys!
# 別倒了哦
Don't drop it!
# 這樹上還有好多
There are still a lot in the tree.
# 這個還有
Here
# 準備下去啦
Let's get ready go get down.
# 不要搞太多
I don't need too many.
# 我又不喝酒
I don't drink any alcohol in fact.
# 我只是拿來送人
I just wanna give it out,
# 拿來給兄弟喝
to my buddy.
# 兄弟喝醉了就好
So that he will be drunk.
# 好去他家玩
Then I can visit him.
# 這叫禮尚往來
This is called reciprocity.
# 兄弟不醉
Without a drunk buddy,
# 我都沒機會
I have no opportunity.
# 就摘了那麼一點點
So we have just a tiny little bit here.
# 不要啦
Enough!
# 回去 拿來
Let's go back, and make some,
# 拿來泡點酒
make some plum liquor,
# 給兄弟喝
for my buddy.
# 我去兄弟家拿點酒來 泡這個梅子酒
Let me get some liquor from my buddy, to make the plum liquor.
# 嗯 可以哦 很不錯
Um! Really not bad. Nice!
# 好 走啦走啦 回家啦
Alright! Let's go, let's go! Let's go home!
# 快點 你拿這個
C'mon! You take this.
# 我拿這個
And I take this.
# 把這個梅子放到這個瓶子上去
We put the plums into the jars.
# 放滿就好了
We just need to fill up each jar.
# 有蒂子的 壞的就不要啊
A stem. The rotten ones need to be thrown away, got it?
# 就這樣裝 裝這個
Just put them in. Put it here.
# 別推過來了啊
Don't push it to my side.
# 夠了 不用裝那麼滿
It's enough. Don't put too many.
# 我這個還沒裝滿
But this one is not yet full.
# 裝多一點
Put more then.
# 等我搞個大瓶子來 全部一起倒掉
Let me put them all into a big jar.
# 嗯 可以 不要裝那麼滿
Um! Alright! Not too many.
# 可以啦 你看 這些都是裝的差不多啦
Alright! Look! These are all almost full.
# 把這酒放下去
So I am pouring the liquor now.
# 我也想來放酒
I wanna pour the liquor too.
# 你不要玩
No way.
# 小孩子不能玩酒的啊
Kids should stay away from liquor, you know.
# 哇 好靚哦
Wa! Beautiful!
# 再加冰糖 這個冰糖 加幾顆冰糖下去
And rock sugar. This is rock sugar. Let me put a few pieces of rock sugar,
# 才不會那個酸
so that it won't be, you know, so sour.
# 這個聽老人家說的
That's what the elderly told us.
# 要不先把冰糖放下去
Alternatively, you can put in the rock sugar first.
# 我也想放冰糖
I wanna help with the rock sugar too.
# 你 你不能放
No, no way.
# 你沒洗手
You haven't washed your hands.
# 我怕你把瓶子打
It's dangerous. You might drop,
# 打破啦
drop the jars.
# 你看 這樣就很靚了哦 這樣
Look! So it's really beautiful now, isn't it?
# 看上去都靚
It's simply eye catching.
# 你看 是不是 冰糖加酒
Look! See? Rock sugar with liquor.
# 誒 沒啦
Eh? No more?
# 就沒啦
No more?
# 你等一下 我再拿一瓶來
Wait! I'm gonna fetch one more bottle.
# 先把它蓋起來
Let me cover it first.
# 這就樣 你看
That's it! Look!
# 這個梅子酒就出來啦
So the plum liquor is done.
# 你看
Look!
# 很漂亮哦
Pretty, isn't it?
# 看上去想不想吃這個 梅子
Do the plums look tasty? Do you wanna try them?
# 不想 為甚麼 (註︰想一句時間太短，Youtube字幕不能太短時間，所以兩句併在一起)
No.
Why not?
# 因為沒吃過
Cuz I've never tried before.
# 放在這裡先
Put them here first.
# 再去拿點酒來
I'm gonna get more liquor.
# 把這個蓋起來
Let me cover them.
# 看 合好啦
Look!
It's done!
# 靚哦
Beautiful!
# 青梅酒
Umeshu
# 你看 這樣就很漂亮了
Look! So it's really pretty.
# 這個梅子
The plums,
# 想都沒想到
could never think of that.
# 它以為我不 不吃它
They thought that I was not, not gonna eat them.
# 我拿來泡酒 我是不吃它
But you know what? I don't eat them. But I use them to make plum liquor.
# 過兩天送給兄弟
I'll give it to my buddy in a few days.
# 你看 這些很靚了哦
Look! They're so beautiful, aren't they?
# 還聞不到酒味 到時候
I can't smell anything now. Later,
# 聞得到酒味到時候再來 (註︰我覺得這句是沒完的，再來甚麼，應該是沒有說下去)
later, when I can sense the aroma...
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 過兩天給兄弟送過去
I'll take it to my buddy.